TheChaosLegion
l want to shine on you,
and always like that dazzling sun.
l will defend you
from all the darkness.
This is the truth from my heart.
lf only our hearts could connect,
l could get you to believe me.
Even if you can't
see it now, don't lose it.
Your kindness won't be in vain.
You'll be carried aloft by the wind
to somewhere that isn't here.
You'll cross the sea and cross time,
and l know you'll blossom one day.
Whatever the day,
l'll be there for you.
l hope l can watch over you
like the sun for all time.
This is the truth from my heart.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
～♪
Nothing's happened since that night.
（バルサ）
あれ以来 何も起こらないな
Still, it's incredible
that we survived at all.
にしても よく生き延びたもんだね
Episode 7
Chagum's
Resolve
See to it that Chagum's image
is engraved here.
（帝(みかど)）チャグムの彫像を彫らせよ
（聖導師(せいどうし)）お言葉ながら…
（帝）分かっておる
With all due respect...
Yes, l know.
末代まで その遺影を残すことが
許されたるは―
l am well aware that only those
who held the rank of mikado...
...are permitted to have their likeness
engraved in stone for perpetuity.
帝の地位に
就いた者のみであることは―
重々(じゅうじゅう) 承知の上だ
Let them mock me as
a foolish father. l care not.
愚かな父親と
そしられようともかまわん
だが チャグムの死によって
この国は水妖(すいよう)から守られたのだ
But it was Chagum's death that spared
this country from the water demon.
lf his noble sacrifice does not warrant
being remembered forever, what does?
その尊い犠牲を
末代に伝えずして何を伝える
Yes, my lord.
The sign of the great drought
should lift now.
これで 乾ノ相(かわきのそう)も晴れよう
l see. So that's how things
turned out yesterday?
（男性１）そうかい 昨日は
そんなことになっちまったのかい
（男性２）ああ まあ今んところは
それも しかたねえと思ってるし―
That's right. For now, at least,
there's nothing to be done about it.
l'm just thankful to be
here with you now.
こうして いられるだけでも
ありがてえ
You don't like noisy crowds?
騒々しいのは嫌いかい？
l find the vigor of the
common people most appealing.
（チャグム）民草の活気に
あふれているさまは気持ちがよい
lt is not at all unpleasant.
余は嫌いではない
Chagum, regular townsfolk
don't speak like that.
チャグム 街の人は
そんな言葉は使わないんだよ
見つかったかい？
Did you find something?
（タンダ）
ああ なかなかの掘り出し物(もん)だ
Yes. lt's quite a hidden gem.
（バルサ）いつから入れる？
When can we move in?
（タンダ）すぐにでも入れるよ
あとは お代だけだな
You can move in right away.
All that's left for you to do is pay for it.
l'll have the same, please.
同じやつを もう１つ
l told Toya and Saya everything.
トーヤとサヤには 全部話したよ
（バルサ）そうかい
Did you now?
They were both pretty angry.
（タンダ）怒ってたぞ ２人とも
Well, l did cause
a lot of trouble for them.
あの子たちには
迷惑をかけたからね
２人は どうしてる？
How are they doing?
Toya is anxious to come back to town.
（タンダ）
トーヤは街に戻りたがってるよ
あの子は
根っからの街っ子だからね
He's a townsman
through and through.
でも まだ早い
But it's still too soon.
Let's eat, shall we?
いただこうか
You know, Balsa, the whole town
is full of gossip about you now.
なあ バルサ
今 街は
お前のウワサで持ちきりなんだぞ
No one would ever guess that
the subject of their gossip...
ウワサの人物が
こんな所で飯を食ってるなんて―
誰も思いつきゃしないよ
...would be sitting here having lunch.
しかしだな…
Maybe so, but...
試してみるかい？
Care to put it to the test?
Excuse me, sir?
ちょっといいかい？
（男性）何じゃい？
What do you want?
Have you heard of a bodyguard
who goes by the name...
あんた 短槍(たんそう)のバルサって用心棒
知ってるかい？
...Balsa the Spear-wielder?
ああ？ バルサだ？
Balsa, did you say?
She's the talk of the town
at the moment.
そいつは 今
この街で１番 熱い話題だな
さては ねえちゃん
最近この街に入ったか？
Let me guess,
you're new in town, aren't you?
まあね
You could say that.
lf you're so curious about her,
l can tell you all that you want to know.
まあ
どうしても知りたいってんなら―
俺様が教えてやろうじゃないか
She's a dastardly villain
who set fire to the palace...
そいつはな 宮に
火 放って皇子を殺し―
...killed the prince and then died in a
huge battle against a thousand pursuers.
あげく 1000の追っ手と
大立ち回りを演じて―
おっちんだ大悪人よ
You don't say! How incredible!
そいつは豪儀だね
当たり前だ もっとも―
Damned right. But as someone
who's crossed swords with her before...
ヤツと剣を交えたことのある俺様に
言わせりゃ―
意外に あっけない最期だったがな
...l have to say her demise
was rather anticlimactic.
へえー あんた そのバルサと
戦ったことがあるのかい？
Oh, my! You mean you've
fought this Balsa person?
That's right! She may have
been a female bodyguard...
おうよ
女用心棒といっても
男顔負けの凶暴なヤツでな
...but she was more ferocious
than any man l've ever met.
Her spear attacks
were so overwhelming...
その槍の すさまじさたるや―
さすがの俺でも
引き分けるのが精いっぱいだった
...that even l could
just barely earn a draw.
いつか 決着を
つけようと思ってたんだが―
l had always hoped to settle
the score with her one day...
...but now l'll never get the chance.
残念なことをしたよ
あんた すごいんだね
（男性）おう
You're unbelievable!
Yes, l am!
See?
ああ…
これは ギショっていう料理でさ
This is a dish called "gisho."
Gisho?
（チャグム）ギショ？
家を継げないヤクーの男が―
This is what they serve a Yakoo man
who won't be taking over...
...as head of his family
to celebrate his having established...
晴れて家族を持ったときの
お祝いとして―
ふるまわれる料理なんだ
...a family of his own.
家族ねえ
A family...
The Yakoo place a high value
on celebrations like this.
ヤクーは
こういう祝い事を大事にするから
These big fava beans
represent the father.
この大きい そら豆が
お父さんで―
赤くて細長いのが お母さん
The red, slender beans
are the mother.
And the little yellow
chickpeas are the child.
黄色くて小さい
ひよこ豆が子供ってわけさ
なんだかね
lf you say so...
Shuga.
（聖導師）シュガよ
There is no longer any need
to decipher the epistles.
もう碑文を読み解く必要は
なくなった
星読みの務めに戻るのだ
You may return to
your star reader duties.
How powerless l am...
（シュガ）
なんという無力 なんという無能
How incompetent l am...
私は 何も成すことができなかった
l wasn't able to accomplish
anything at all.
Thank you for your hard work.
（トロガイ）ご苦労だったね
l'll be taking a bit of a shortcut,
so this is where we part company.
ちょっと近道をしたいんで―
お前はここまでじゃ
（トロガイ）これで オオカミは
寄ってこないだろうが―
This should keep the wolves away,
but be careful all the same.
一応は気をつけるんだよ
Take care.
達者でな ほれ
Off with you.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
わあー
Come to think of it...
（タンダ）そういや―
今までだったら お前の仕事は
もう終わってるんだよな
...if this was any of your previous jobs,
you'd be done at this point.
You would be done?
終わりなのか？
普通 用心棒稼業ってのは
敵を退けたら終わりだからね
ln the bodyguard business...
...the job is typically over once
you've driven off your enemies.
Mind if we make a quick stop here?
ちょっといいかい？
傷に効く薬草を切らしちまったんだ
l'm all out of herbs
for treating wounds.
Good afternoon.
こんにちは
Welcome, sir.
（店主）いらっしゃいまし
いつもの薬草
分けてもらいたいんだけど
l'd like some of my usual medicinal
herbs if you have them in stock.
Right this way.
（店主）こちらへどうぞ
Don't touch that without asking.
（バルサ）勝手に触るんじゃないよ
もういいのかい？
You're done already?
He's getting what l need
from his storeroom.
今 蔵から出してもらってる
Listen, are you sure you're up to
handling things from now on?
なあ お前これから
うまくやっていけるのか？
Handle what?
何が？
（タンダ）
一生 面倒見るってことは―
Looking after someone
your whole life...
言ってみりゃ
母親になるようなもんだろ
...is basically the same
as being a mother.
そういや そうだね
Now that you mention it,
l suppose it is.
How long have you been
an herbologist, Tanda?
タンダは
いつから薬草師をしておるのだ？
そうだな…
Let me think...
l guess l started mixing
medicines when l was 12...
12のころには 師匠が作った
薬草図鑑を見ながら―
...using the reference guides
my mentor made.
薬の調合してたかな
Then you started working
at quite a young age.
ずいぶんと早くから
働いておったのじゃな
l was the youngest child.
俺は末っ子だから
いずれは自立して―
l had to learn self-reliance...
...so that l'd be able to
earn my own living one day.
１人で食ってかなくちゃ
ならなかったんでね
Well, l'll catch up
with you after l make...
（タンダ）
それじゃ俺は いったん戻って
残りのものを買ってから行くから
...a quick trip back and
buy the rest of what l need.
All right.
（バルサ）分かった
どこへ行くのじゃ？
Where are we going?
（バルサ）
うん？ 家賃を払いに行くのさ
To pay the rent.
家賃？ 民草の家とは
金を払わねば住めぬのか？
Rent?
Commoners cannot stay in their homes
unless they pay money to do so?
You can't get anything
if you don't pay for it with money.
（バルサ）金を払わなきゃ
何だって手に入らないさ
l understand the concept
of exchanging money for goods.
金と物を交換するのは分かる
l also understand
paying money for services...
バルサが
余を守ってくれたように―
働いてもらったことに対して
金を払うのも分かる
...like when you were
paid money to protect me.
But...
だが…
宿にだって金は払っただろ？
l paid money at the inn, remember?
One pays money even to sleep?
But it was l who slept, not you!
寝るのにも金を払うのか？
寝たのは余じゃぞ
寝たって 金はもらえないよ
l couldn't take a client's money
if l slept on the job.
To a commoner, money rules
all aspects of life, does it not?
市井とは なんとも
金が幅を利かせておるのだな
まあね
You could say that.
母君から頂いた財宝も
全て渡してしまったしな
And we've handed over all of
the treasure given to us by Mother.
l can rest easy now. You seem like
an honest, upstanding family to me.
（男性）
身持ちの堅そうな家族で安心したよ
Forgive me, but the boy
is someone else's child.
（バルサ）申し訳ない
あの子は他人の子でしてね
Due to various circumstances,
he was left in our care.
故あって預かってるんです
（男性）ああ そうか
l see. Taking in someone else's
child is no trivial matter.
まあ 他人の子を預かるというのは
簡単なことではないからのう
それはそれで いいよ
That speaks well of you too.
これで よろしくお願いします
l hope you will find this acceptable.
There's no need to be so generous.
（男性）ここまで気を遣わんでも
ええんだがのう
この代金分
わしが生きるとはかぎらんしな
After all, l might not live out the term
that this much money will cover.
Of course, if my wife were still alive...
まあ ばあさんが生きてれば―
娘らの やっかいになんぞ
なることもなかったんだが
...l wouldn't have to impose on
my daughter and her family.
Forgive my useless rambling.
あっ… 詮ないことを
しゃべってしもうたな
Take good care of the place.
大事に使ってくだされ
（バルサ）はい
We will.
どうしたんだい？
（チャグム）いや…
What's the matter?
Nothing.
l wonder how Jiguro felt
when he was in this position?
ジグロは どう思ってたんだろうね
l suppose when you're
raised by a man of few words...
無口な人に育てられると―
しゃべれない人間に
なっちまうんだろうな
...you grow up to be
a silent person yourself.
But that won't do, will it?
それじゃダメだね
ここが今日から私たちが住む家だよ
This is the house that we
will be living in from now on.
We are going to take up
residence here?
ここに住まうのか？
（バルサ）そうだよ
That's right.
l never would've guessed one would
pay in gold coins to live in a water mill.
よもや金貨を払って
水車小屋で暮らそうとはな
確かに掘り出し物ではあるね
lt's a hidden gem, that's for certain.
Why don't we give it a try?
Who knows, it might be fun.
動かしてみようか
案外 楽しいかもしれないよ
You know how to operate
a waterwheel, Balsa?
バルサは水車も動かせるのか？
（バルサ）まあね
Oh, yes. lsn't it nice to be living in
a house that has devices like this?
こんな仕掛けがある家も
悪くないだろ？
l think the roof might need
to be thatched again, though.
でも 屋根は ふき替えないと
ダメかもしれないね
l think you may be right.
そのようじゃな
But l expect that will cost money too.
でも また金がかかるのう
l'm back.
（タンダ）ただいま
ちょっと買いすぎだよ
（タンダ）まあ いいじゃないか
You bought too much.
Don't worry about it.
待たせたね
Sorry l took so long.
l wanted to treat you two to a fine meal...
２人に おいしいものを
食わせてやろうと思って―
...and by the time l'd bought
everything, it had gotten late.
いろいろ買い込んでいたら
遅くなっちまったよ
lt'll be ready in no time.
すぐ用意するからな
Chagum, do you feel sick?
チャグム あんた
どこか具合でも悪いのかい？
No, l am fine.
どこも悪くない
バルサのおかげで息災じゃ
l am in good health thanks to you.
今まで さんざん
えらい目に遭ったんだからな
You've been through quite an ordeal
over these past few days.
今日くらいは おいしいものを
たらふく食べたって―
There's no harm in filling yourself up
with a hearty meal for once.
罰は当たらんさ
２人に話があるのだ
There is something that l wish
to discuss with the two of you.
今まで世話になった
l thank you for all that
you have done for me.
この耳飾りは 余の感謝のしるしだ
Please accept this earring
as a token of my gratitude.
受けた恩義の数々は 一生忘れぬ
l owe you a debt of gratitude that
l shall never forget as long as l live.
これ以上
そなたたちに苦労をかけられぬ
l cannot bring myself to
impose on you any longer.
l have decided that from
today forward, l shall fend for myself.
余は これから
１人で生きていこうと決めた
l thought you'd been acting funny...
様子が変だと思っていたら あんた
そんなこと考えていたのかい？
So is that what you've
been brooding over all day?
さすがというか なんというか…
l guess l shouldn't be surprised.
You find this amusing?
おかしいか？
Chagum, how would you
support yourself if you left us now?
チャグム あんた ここを出て
どうやって生きていくんだい？
余もタンダほどではないが
薬や動物の知識はある
lt may not be as extensive as Tanda's...
...but l have knowledge of
medicines and animals as well.
それで なんとか やっていける
l will get by somehow.
You silly boy...
バカだねえ
You can stay here as long as you like.
お前は
ずっと ここにいていいんだよ
お前の母親と会ったとき
そう約束しただろ
When l met your mother,
that's what l promised her, remember?
それに この世にはね
And besides, there are
lots of people in this world...
金なんか もらわなくったって―
...who wouldn't turn away a boy like you
even if they weren't paid to take you in.
あんたみたいな子供を
ほっとけないヤツが―
結構いるもんなのさ
But money is needed
to survive, is it not?
でも 生きていくためには
金がかかるのだろう？
Don't worry. There's no need for you
to give that a moment's thought.
安心おし
そんなこと お前は
一切 考えなくたっていいんだから
Thank you, Balsa...
ありがとう バルサ
乾ノ相は消えていない！
The sign of the great drought
has not disappeared!
As l sat huddled and alone, holding
back the tears on those nights...
When it felt like l was about
to succumb to my doubts...
...there you were,
at my side before l knew it.
lt was none other than you
who was there for me.
l keep wishing, "l want to be strong."
l stumble and hurt myself again.
But because l have you to believe in,
l can get back to my feet.
l simply want to tell
my dear one, "Thank you."
At the top of my lungs,
again and again.
l call out to my precious loved one.
ls my voice reaching you?
ln this world that always changes,
human warmth never does.
l'm certain l sensed the presence
of the one that l hold dear.
～♪
Next Time
A visit is paid to Balsa's
longstanding blacksmith.
There they are reunited...
...with someone unexpected.
Someone other than the blacksmith.
Next time,
"The Swordsmith."
Episode 8
The Swordsmith
What is it that qualifies one...
...to wield the ultimate blade?